Hello all and welcome to our second tutorial. In this tutorial as we can recall from the
previous one we have installed Docker and now we will play with it to install web server
and SQL server and then we will connect the SQL and web server together. So the first
step here we will pull a Docker image that has both Apache and latest PHP on it. So first
before we can pull the Docker let's create a permanent directory the permanent directory
we create by makedier-p which means permanent and tilde which means home direction
and www folder which will contain the default websites for the Apache web server and then
we will make change modification to give it the right to have read/write executes for users
and the same for groups and for other only read and execute and it should work without any issue
because in the web server 775 permission is enough okay to this we give it to this directory
and then we will have you know some contents to be displayed and when just for testing purposes
and we'll put it this information for of PHP information function into info.php
just for testing the functionality for the web server. So first here let's create a directory
okay and of course when we try to change the writes should be asked me to do it with the sudo
okay didn't ask me that's good because I didn't make a huge change for 777 that's good
and now let's put the information of PHP information function into the www folder
okay so for so good we now proceed with running the server image and we'll publish it with using
both both ports of 80 and 443 so first we'll not run a just run a docker okay we'll run a docker
but that it is named PHP Apache to include latest version of PHP and Apache and to specify
P4 ports P8080 and P4043 start and end all the ports and we'll mount it to a writeable volume
okay say you will mount it to www for www html and to with the map drive z okay and do we choose the
PHP 88.5 with Apache server so let's first run this docker
we should run it directly without using sudo because we have added the users as you can recall
from the previous recording we add users m number to the docker group
okay there is something with permission
I remember that we have done the permission but anyway it's not a problem
we can run the docker we just do if we face the problem like this that's not an issue
okay now we have waited or pause the video till the docker is put and now we can see that
this is the ID for the container and it is downloaded with the version of PHP 8.5 okay so far so good so
for now we can test with HTTP access for the local host so let's try it let's open for example here
let's open local host with the firefox
okay as you can see here it is successfully it can successfully run with a local host
and info.hp display everything okay but if you can see now if we can press HTTPS
like here if we add s it should not working okay and it's a secure connection failed okay
why this happens because simply we didn't create yet the SSL certificates or self-science certificates
and we should create it before we can enable the SSL module and create a default SSL website
so let's do this to enable the SSL to work correctly okay we need first to connect to the docker
we have already created the docker let's go back to our terminal for example here if we type docker
ps
okay if you can see here we have two docker
we have the one this is the latest one 8.5 and we have the hello word that we have run
that we ran in the previous record okay it's about one day and this we run it it's running only
in three minutes and it is existed but now this PHP it is running without any issue okay that's cool
so let's try to enter this to execute some comments in the my-php Apache so we need to type the
comment like that okay docker executes - it and we need to empty tweets bash and now we need to first
enable SSL module and we need to take care to follow these steps because you need first to enable
SSL module and then create the certificates before you can enable the sites if you for example
enable SSL certificates and then create SSL and try to refresh the Apache web server or restart
it before creating the certificate it will cause the problem and maybe your container will crash
so you need to be careful when applying this in the same sequence or so first let's execute
these comments to enable SSL module on the one hour Apache web server
okay we will not activate it now we'll activate it later we'll make a graceful restart later
after creating the certificates and enabling the SSL sites let's create the self-sign certificates
okay this will be valid for one year this is RSA encryption key
okay this will be the key which will be should be transformed into dot CRT file and this is the subject
subject name okay or canonical name will be local so we have now this is the hash our hash certificates
and now let's enable the SSL sites
okay so now I see I think we are good okay to proceed with enabling the websites or before
we can test the websites or we make any restarts okay we need first to before we do a graceful
restart to the Apache we need to execute these comments okay what is this set comment this set
comment avoids issue because of having some SSL certificates it is the default ones that it is used
by Apache you need to replace them okay with instead of being grand with PM to be CRT okay
this comment will execute will transform it to be Apache dot CRT okay for and this snail key
okay will be replaced with Apache dot key so you need to have both certificate Apache dot CRT and Apache
dot key okay this is very important to run okay so let's go here we are already in our
in the correct prompts so you need to execute this comments okay perfect now we are ready to
restart the Docker let's restart it it starts my PHP Apache we'll do a graceful restart
okay this is normal warning because we have already this is the net IP address inside of my
VMware which will be assigned to the container and this is just a warning message that you should
use a fully qualified domain not the IP address okay so now if we can if we want to try HTTPS
it should now work without it as you can see now it's just give you warning but if you can click
on advance accept the risk and voila it is working without any issue so now we have finished
the task of running the web server and we have published the 80 port and access the it by using
our PHP dot info and also we access the SSL which also HTTPS to display the small testing page of
PHP okay let's move to the other part here we'll pull the Docker image I will use the option
A I will use my SQL I will pull the Docker image with my SQL not Maria database okay this this one
so as we we have done in the previous steps we'll do the same but we will just make a very critical
change for the permission we created directory to point to my SQL data but for the change mode
it will be 777 not 775 if you set it 775 the database will run I was continuing to run
but it will stop maybe after few seconds five seconds for example because you need to have
food permission for users groups and ask you to have full permission okay so you need to take
care for that part so let's create here my SQL data
let's clear this